Guide to the Stanford University, Stanford Center for Japanese Studies, Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University, Stanford Center for Japanese Studies, records
1936-1964
1960-1964
SC0265
Stanford University. Stanford Center for Japanese Studies.
2.25 Linear feet (5 boxes)
The collection largely contains correspondence with some memoranda, proposals, financial documents, class materials, and photographs. Much of the correspondence is that of Robert H. Brower, John D. Goheen, Thomas C. Smith, and Kurt Steiner; other correspondents include T. E. Gore, Paul Hanna, Shinzo Kaji, George Kerr, Hideo Kishimoto, William H. McCullough, and John L. Mothershead, Jr. Records pre-dating the Center occur in Goheen's correspondence and include George Kerr's prospectus for an Institute for American Studies in Japan, 1947, and his syllabus for a Japanese literature class, 1936. The photographs primarily document the first year of the program.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
This collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 48 hours in advance of intended use.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
The Stanford Center for Japanese Studies in Tokyo was established in April 1961. The purpose was to provide undergraduate and graduate students from Stanford and other universities with the opportunity to pursue intensive study in Japanese and Asian affairs for a full calendar year. John D. Goheen was its founding director.
Description of the Collection
The collection largely contains correspondence with some memoranda, proposals, financial documents, class materials, and photographs. Much of the correspondence is that of Robert H. Brower, John D. Goheen, Thomas C. Smith, and Kurt Steiner; other correspondents include T. E. Gore, Paul Hanna, Shinzo Kaji, George Kerr, Hideo Kishimoto, William H. McCullough, and John L. Mothershead, Jr. Records pre-dating the Center occur in Goheen's correspondence and include George Kerr's prospectus for an Institute for American Studies in Japan, 1947, and his syllabus for a Japanese literature class, 1936. The photographs primarily document the first year of the program.
Access Terms
Brower, Robert H., 1923-1988.; Goheen, John D.; Hanna, Paul Robert, 1902-1988.; Kaji, Shinzo.; Kerr, George H., 1911-; Kishimoto, Hideo, 1903-1964.; McCullough, William H.; Mothershead, John L.; Smith, Thomas C. (Thomas Carlyle), 1916-2004; Stanford University. Stanford Center for Japanese Studies.; Steiner, Kurt, 1912-; Foreign study.; Intercultural education.; Japan--Study and teaching.; Photoprints.
Collection Contents
- Aoki, Haruo, correspondence, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Brower, R. to J. Goheen, memos, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Brower, R. from J. Goheen, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Budget for Tokyo Center, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Carnegie Corporation, correspondence, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Carnegie Corporation, proposal for Stanford-in-Tokyo, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Consultive Committee, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Consultive Committee, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, general, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, general, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, general, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, general, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Courses at Tokyo Center (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Courses, departmental permission (Box 1, Folder 14)
- East-West Center (U. of Hawaii), correspondence (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Faculty Applicants, correspondence (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Fahs, Burton, correspondence, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Finance (documents and correspondence) (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Ford Foundation, correspondence, 1961-1963 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Furukawa, Harukaze, correspondence, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Future of Tokyo Center, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- General information on Center (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Goheen, John, correspondence, 1960-63 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Goheen, John, correspondence, 1957, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Goheen, John, correspondence, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Goheen, John, correspondence, mostly with John L. Mothershead, Jr. at Stanford University Dept. of Philosophy, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Goheen, John, correspondence, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Includes carbon copy of Annual Report to the Ford Foundation from the Committee on East Asian Studies, 1961
- Goheen, John, correspondence re Fullbright-Hays award for lecturing in Japan, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Gore, T. E., correspondence, 1961-1964 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Graduate division, correspondence and memos, 1961-1963 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Hanna, Paul, correspondence (mostly with Goheen and John Singleton), 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- International Christian University (Tokyo), correspondence, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Inter-University Organization [Inter-University Center for Japanese Studies in Japan], correspondence and memos, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Inter-University Organization, proposal for support, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Japan-America Cultural Conference, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Japanese students coming to U. S., correspondence, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Jodai, Tano (President of Tokyo Women's University), visit to Stanford, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Kaji, Shinzo, correspondence, 1960-1964 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Kaya, Seiji, correspondence, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Keio University and Summer Program, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Kerr, George, correspondence, 1956-1963 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Includes his prospectus for an institute for American Studies in Japan, 1947, and a syllabus for a Japanese literature class, 1936.
- Kishimoto, Hideo, correspondence, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Kurata, Bunsaku, correspondence in support of his teaching, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Kyoto University (Goheen to Chancellor Setsuji Otsuka), 1962 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Language program in Tokyo, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Language Requirements Study, correspondence, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Library account (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Liu, James, correspondence, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- McCray, Porter (John D. Rockefeller 3rd Fund), correspondence, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- McCullough, William, correspondence, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Mayekawa, Kisaku, correspondence, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Map of Tokyo (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Miyaji, Hiroshi (Goheen's letter re), 1960 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Mizota, George S., correspondence, 1960-1963 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Moving of Tokyo Center, memo, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Murai, Sukenaga, correspondence, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- NDEA Title VI Fellowships (Box 3, Folder 17)
- NDFL Recommendations, Asian Languages (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Nishimura, Iwao (Fulbright committee) (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Non Inter-University Comm. Centers for Japanese Studies (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Notes, etc., on exploratory trip for center, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Ohama, Nobumoto, correspondence, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Personnel, Tokyo Center (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Publicity; includes typescript report by Kenneth B. Pyle for the Daily, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Recommendation requests for students at Stanford Center (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Registrar's Office (re classes), 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Report to the President, 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Shively, Donald H., correspondence, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Smith, Thomas, correspondence, 1962-1963 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Smith, Thomas, memos from Goheen #1-92, 1962-1963 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Smith, Thomas, memos out #1-218 with accompanying documents, 1962-1963 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Smith, Thomas, miscellaneous numbered memos out with accompanying documents, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Staff: applicants for work (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Stanford Alumni Association, Japan (report on Tokyo Center Fund Account), 1961 Aug 1 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Steiner, Kurt, correspondence, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Sterling, J. E. Wallace - Tokyo trip, correspondence, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Students: advice to (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Students: awards (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Students: miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Students: participants (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Students: reactions (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Takamura, Shohei, correspondence, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Telegrams (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Unfinished business (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Uyeda, Seizi, correspondence, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Viglielmo, V. H., correspondence, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Visitors to and from Tokyo (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Wakeijuku contract [for use of space], 1962 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Photographs, arriving in Tokyo (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Photographs, public event, 1961 Apr 21 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Photographs, Sterling at ceremonies (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Photographs, Sterling and others at a meal (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Photographs, public gathering (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Photographs, classroom scenes (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Photographs, American students - various scenes (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Photographs, Stanford Center (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Photographs, social scenes (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Photographs, dining scenes (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Photographs, group in front of Buddha statue (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Photographs, dinner event and group strolling (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Photographs, Goheen with Japanese faculty, 1961 Mar 22 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Photographs, at Waseda (?) (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Photographs, various groups (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Photographs, Japanese potter (?) at work (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Photographs, miscellaneous (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Photographs, cultural performance (Box 5, Folder 18)